JINGYAN WANG

312 Groseclose Building, 755 Ferst Drive NW, Atlanta, GA 30332

Web: https://jingyanw.github.io/ Email: jingyanw@gatech.edu

RESEARCH OVERVIEW

My research interests are in statistical machine learning and fairness. I study the foundations of high-stakes decision making, such as in hiring, admissions and peer review. I draw inspiration from psychology to model real-world phenomena, develop algorithms with provable theoretical guarantees using tools from statistics and computer science, conduct crowdsourcing experiments, and implement policy changes that have made practical impact. My research is interdisciplinary, and has been published in the fields of statistics, machine learning, economics and computation, human computation, and artificial intelligence.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Georgia Institute of Technology President's and Algorithms and Randomness Center (ARC) Postdoctoral Fellow H. Milton Stewart School of Industrial and Systems Engineering	2021 – present
Hosts: Ashwin Pananjady, Juba Ziani	
Simons Laufer Mathematical Sciences Institute (SLMath) Research member	10-12.2023
Program: Algorithms, Fairness, and Equity	
Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing Visiting postdoctoral fellow	11.2021
Program: Computational Complexity of Statistical Inference	
EDUCATION	
Carnegie Mellon University	2015 – 2021
Ph.D., School of Computer Science	
Thesis: Towards Understanding and Mitigating Biases	
Advisor: Nihar B. Shah	
University of California, Berkeley	2011 - 2015
Bachelor of Science, Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences	
Minor in Mathematics	
Graduated with Highest Honors	
AWARDS	
Rising Stars in EECS Workshop	2023
Rising Stars in Data Science Workshop, University of Chicago	2022

A

Rising Stars in EECS Workshop	2023
Rising Stars in Data Science Workshop, University of Chicago	2022
Best Lightning Talk from College of Engineering, Fall 2022 Georgia Tech Postdoc Research Symposium	2022
Best Research Talk from College of Engineering, Spring 2022 Georgia Tech Postdoc Research Symposium	ı 2022
Ronald J. and Carol T. Beerman President's Postdoctoral Fellowship, Georgia Tech	2021
ARC (Algorithms & Randomness Center) Fellowship, Georgia Tech	2021
Best Paper Award Nomination, AAMAS 2019	
Best Student Paper Award, AAMAS 2019	

Travel scholarship, AAAI 2020, AAMAS 2019, WiML and HCML workshops at Neur	IPS 2019
Departmental Citation, UC Berkeley Recognition of outstanding undergraduate achievement within the department awarded to one graduating	2015 senior annually
James H. Eaton Memorial Scholarship, UC Berkeley For a keen sense of creativity and inventiveness	2015
Kevin K. Gong Memorial Scholarship for Bright Minds and Big Hearts, UC Berkeley For passion about using technology to better the world	2015
Arthur M. Hopkin Award, UC Berkeley For seriousness of purpose and high academic achievement	2014
Berkeley Club of Hong Kong Undergraduate Scholarship, UC Berkeley	2014
Edward Frank Kraft Award for Freshmen, UC Berkeley	2012
Dean's honors list, UC Berkeley	Fall 2011 – Spring 2015

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS AND UNDER REVIEW

- **Jingyan Wang**, Ashwin Pananjady *Modeling and Correcting Bias in Sequential Evaluation* Under major revision in Operations Research, 2023.
- Jingyan Wang, Ivan Stelmakh, Yuting Wei, Nihar B. Shah
 Debiasing Evaluations That Are Biased by Evaluations

 Accepted with minor revision in Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), 2023.
- Lei Tian, Jingyan Wang, Laura Waller
 3D Differential Phase-Contrast Microscopy with Computational Illumination Using an LED Array
 Optics Letters 39 (1326-1329), 2014.

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS (* indicates alphabetical order)

- Austin Xu, Andrew D. McRae, Jingyan Wang, Mark A. Davenport, Ashwin Pananjady
 Perceptual Adjustment Queries and an Inverted Measurement Paradigm for Low-Rank Metric Learning Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2023.
- **Jingyan Wang**, Ashwin Pananjady *Modeling and Correcting Bias in Sequential Evaluation*ACM Conference on Economics and Computation (EC), 2023.
- Gregory Kehne*, Ariel D. Procaccia*, **Jingyan Wang*** *Recruitment Strategies That Take a Chance*Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2022.
- Jingyan Wang, Carmel Baharav, Nihar B. Shah, Anita Williams Woolley, R. Ravi Allocation Schemes in Analytic Evaluation: Applicant-Centric Holistic or Attribute-Centric Segmented? AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP), 2022.
- Komal Dhull, Jingyan Wang, Nihar B. Shah, Yuanzhi Li, R. Ravi A Heuristic for Statistical Seriation Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI), 2021.
- Jingyan Wang, Ivan Stelmakh, Yuting Wei, Nihar B. Shah Debiasing Evaluations That Are Biased by Evaluations AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2021.

• Jingyan Wang, Nihar B. Shah, R. Ravi

Stretching the Effectiveness of MLE from Accuracy to Bias for Pairwise Comparisons International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2020.

• Jingyan Wang, Nihar B. Shah

Your 2 is My 1, Your 3 is My 9: Handling Arbitrary Miscalibrations in Ratings International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS), 2019.

Best Student Paper Award

Nomination for Best Paper Award

Appeared as invited paper "Ranking and Rating Rankings and Ratings" in Sister Conference Track at AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2020.

• Jingyan Wang, Olga Russakovsky, Deva Ramanan

The More You Look, the More You See: towards General Object Understanding through Recursive Refinement Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV), 2018.

• KV Rashmi, Preetum Nakkiran, Jingyan Wang, Nihar B. Shah, Kannan Ramchandran

Having Your Cake and Eating It Too: Jointly Optimal Codes for I/O, Storage and Network-bandwidth in Distributed Storage Systems

Conference on File and Storage Technologies (FAST), 2015.

Picked as the Best Paper by StorageMojo

Steve Yadlowsky, Preetum Nakkiran, Jingyan Wang, Rishi Sharma, Laurent El Ghaoui.
 Iterative Hard Thresholding for Keyword Extraction from Large Text Corpora International Conference on Machine Learning and Applications (ICMLA), 2014.

INVITED TALKS

Understanding and Improving Evaluation: People, Algorithms, and Design	
EECS Special Seminar, Massachusetts Institute of Technology	2023
IDEAL Institute, Northwestern University	2023
Ethics & Algorithms Seminar, University of California, Santa Cruz	2023
Peking University	2023
Carnegie Mellon University	2022
Modeling and Correcting Bias in Sequential Evaluation	
BLISS Seminar, UC Berkeley	2023
Algorithms, Combinatorics and Optimization Research Network (ACORN) Meeting	2023
Rising Stars in Data Science Workshop, University of Chicago	2022
INFORMS Annual Meeting	2022
Information Theory and Applications Workshop (ITA)	2022
Debiasing Evaluations That Are Biased by Evaluations	
INFORMS Annual Meeting	2023
Women in EconCS, International Joint Conference on Theoretical Computer Science (IJTCS)	2021
Towards Understanding and Mitigating Biases	
Georgia Institute of Technology	2021
Harvard University	2021
Nanyang Technological University	2021
Peking University	2019
Understanding Biases in Assessment Problems	
The Auton Lab, Carnegie Mellon University	2019

• The More You Look, the More You See: Towards General Object Understanding through Recursive Refinement National Robotics Engineering Center (NREC) 2017

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

 Co-Instructor: ISYE 8813 (Algorithmic Foundations of Ethical Machine Learning), Georgia Tech 	Fall 2023
Guest Lecturer: IST402 (Crowdsourcing and Crowd-AI Systems), Penn State Plantage (Parkers of the All Systems)	Spring 2023
PIC 16B (Python with Applications II), UCLA ISYE 6740 (Computational Data Analysis), Georgia Tech	Winter 2023 Fall 2022
• Teaching Assistant: 16-720 (Computer Vision), CMU	Fall 2017
• Lab Assistant: EE 20N (Signals and Systems), UC Berkeley	Fall 2013

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

- Journal reviewer: Annals of Statistics (2020), Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research (2022, 2023)
- Conference reviewer: ICLR (2024), CHI (2024), WWW (2024), NeurIPS (2023), AAAI (2021, 2022, 2023, 2024), ISIT (2021), STOC (2020), WiML NeurIPS (2019)
- Program committee member: FAccT (2023), WINE (2023), HCOMP (2022, 2023), Learning with Strategic Agents workshop, AAMAS (2022)
- Admissions committee member: Robotics Institute Summer Scholars (2019)
- Student volunteer: AAAI (2020), AAMAS (2019), ICML (2016)

OUTREACH ACTIVITIES

Speaker, Seminar on Diversity, Equity, Inclusion (DEI) and Bias, GT INFORMS Student Chapter	2022
Presenter, Mission Possible Summer Camp, Georgia Tech Led activities for high-school students to learn about crowdsourcing through storytelling the DARPA Red Balloon Chall	2022
Grand award judge, Regeneron International Science and Engineering Fair (ISEF)	2022
Panelist, Tea with Summer Undergraduates, CMU	2019
Interview participant, the Girls Who Code Featured in the article https://womenincs.github.io/future.html	2019
Student volunteer, PhD student open house, CMU	2019, 2021
Graduate student mentor, Robotics Institute Summer Scholars (RISS), CMU Mentored undergraduate students through the graduate school application process and provided suggestions on the wri	2018 ting material
Outreach officer and webmaster, Society of Women Engineers (SWE) Organized middle and high school outreach events and designed the chapter's website	2011 – 2015
Member, Eta Kappa Nu Honor Society (HKN)	2013 - 2015
NDUSTRIAL EXPERIENCE	

IN

Facebook Inc.	6.2014 - 8.2014
Software Engineering Intern, Privacy Infrastructure Team	
EMC Corporation	6.2013 - 8.2013
Software Engineering Intern, Advanced Storage Division	

REFERENCES

• Nihar B. Shah (nihars@cs.cmu.edu)

Associate Professor

Machine Learning Department; Computer Science Department

Carnegie Mellon University

• R. Ravi (ravi@andrew.cmu.edu)

Professor

Tepper School of Business

Carnegie Mellon University

• Ashwin Pananjady (ashwinpm@gatech.edu)

Assistant Professor

School of Industrial and Systems Engineering; School of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Georgia Institute of Technology

• Juba Ziani (jziani3@gatech.edu)

Assistant Professor

School of Industrial and Systems Engineering

Georgia Institute of Technology

• Yuting Wei (ytwei@wharton.upenn.edu)

Assistant Professor

Department of Statistics and Data Science

The Wharton School

University of Pennsylvania

• Ariel Procaccia (arielpro@seas.harvard.edu)

Professor

Computer Science, School of Engineering and Applied Sciences

Harvard University